Guide to the Esther Ziskind Weltman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Esther Ziskind Weltman papers
1950-1987
MS 1561
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The papers consist of correspondence and reports documenting the activities of the Jacob Ziskind Trust for Charitable Purposes, including requests for assistance, negotiations for gifts, and reports on the status and uses of gifts.
Weltman, Esther Ziskind
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David L. Weltman, 1995.
Biographical / Historical
Esther Ziskind Weltman was born in Lowell, Massachusetts. She graduated from Smith College in 1922 and received a master's degree in education from Harvard in 1924. In 1950, upon the death of her brother, Jacob, she became trustee of the Jacob Ziskind Trust for Charitable Purposes. Abraham Berkowitz served as co-trustee. The Trust has provided funds for buildings and programs at many institutions of higher learning and research, including Smith College, Brandeis University, Hebrew Union College, the Hebrew University, the Jewish Theological Seminary of America, Technion - Israel Institute of Technology, the University of the Negev, and the Weizmann Institute of Science. The Trust has also supported the Judaica Studies Program at Yale and established the Ziskind Collection of Greek Manuscripts in the Yale University Library. Esther Weltman served as a trustee of the National Council of Jewish Women's Scholarship Clearinghouse, the Massachusetts Board of Higher Education, the New York Medical Center, Hebrew College, and the American International College. She died in Cambridge, Massachusetts, April 30, 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence and reports documenting the activities of the Jacob Ziskind Trust for Charitable Purposes, including requests for assistance, negotiations for gifts, and reports on the status and uses of gifts.
Jews -- United States -- Charities; Universities and colleges -- United States -- Finance; Berkowitz, Abraham; Weltman, Esther Ziskind; Ziskind, Jacob, -1950; Brandeis University; Hebrew Union College; Jacob Ziskind Trust for Charitable Purposes; Jewish Theological Seminary of America; Mekhon Ṿaitsman le-madaʻ; Smith College; Ṭekhniyon, Makhon ṭekhnologi le-Yiśraʼel; Universiṭah ha-ʻIvrit bi-Yerushalayim; Universiṭat ha-Negev; Yale University
- Inventory
  - Obituary of Jacob Ziskind, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administration of the Jacob Ziskind Trust for Charitable Purposes [re: issues following the death of co-trustee Abraham Berkowitz], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation [re: gift for the construction of the B'nai B'rith Hillel building at Boston University], 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brandeis University [re: the Jacob Ziskind Visiting Professorships and the Jacob Ziskind Institute in Continuing Education in Jewish Studies], 1952-1969, 1975, 1983, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 8)
  - Hadassah [re: gifts for construction and medical equipment], 1956, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hebrew Union College [re: the Jacob Ziskind Memorial Fellowship for graduate study], 1954-1966, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hebrew University [re: the Jacob Ziskind Visiting Scholars Program and the Jacob Ziskind Professorship of Biochemistry], 1959-1963, 1966-1977, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Henrietta Szold Institute for Child and Youth Welfare [re: educational programs for gifted Oriental youth in Israel], 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary of America [re: the Jacob Ziskind Memorial Fund for research fellowships and publications], 1952-1962, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13 - 15)
  - Smith College [re: gifts for spectroscopic laboratories, Ziskind House (dormitory), the Jacob Ziskind Lectures on the History of American Civilization, and contributions to the alumni fund, research grants, tutorial program, and other Smith College programs], 1950-1978 (Box 2, Folder 16 - 18)
  - Technion - Israel Institute of Technology [re: gift for Jacob Ziskind Student Hostel (dormitory) and other building projects], 1958-1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - University of the Negev [re: the Jacob Ziskind Visiting Professors Fund], 1971-1973, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Weizmann Institute of Science [re: gifts for building projects, endowment, and scholarships], 1952-1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Yale University [re: gifts for scholarships, the purchase of Greek manuscripts, support of the Yale Judaica Series, and the Ziskind Fund], 1956-1964, 1967, 1969, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22 - 23)